John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland of British Columbia fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland of British Columbia fonds
1922 - 2013
F-1
Q106643956
21.45 m of textual records 56 photographs
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION: 1 photograph located in F-1-2-6-11 21 photographs located in F-1-3-1-0-29 23 photographs located in F-1-3-1-0-30 1 photograph located in F-1-3-1-0-31
John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland of British Columbia
The John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland of British Columbia (JHSLM) takes its name and its spirit from the 18th century English prison reformer who observed unjust social conditions in prisons, both as a prisoner of war during the Seven Years War, and as High Sheriff of Bedfordshire, a post which included the task of inspecting local prisons. The suffering that John Howard endured and witnessed led him to become a lifelong advocate for criminal and social justice reform. Throughout his life he demonstrated a firm belief that every citizen must ultimately accept his or her individual responsibility for the criminal justice system.
The society began as the John Howard Society of British Columbia, established in Vancouver in 1931. It was the first John Howard Society in Canada. The objects of the Society as outlined in its Constitution (1932) were to seek to remove conditions which lead persons into crime; to befriend the first offender; to work for the wise and just treatment of those confirmed to penal institutions; to guide and help the mothers, wives and children of men in prison; to help discharged and paroled men and women to re-establish themselves; and to work for wise and just legislation with reference to court procedures and penal administration.
The Society has grown so that in 2020 there are over 60 John Howard Societies across Canada with a national office in Ottawa.
Throughout its history, the professional staff of the Society have been responsible for visiting regularly or being on-call to various correctional facilities throughout British Columbia. These include prisons, forest camps, community correctional centres and half-way houses. Staff offer counseling, advocacy, pre-release planning, educational guidance and develop self-help groups such as Alcoholics Anonymous and the Seventh Step Society. Staff also assist clients in the courts offering pre-sentence intervention, alternatives to incarceration, and counseling. In addition, family members are supported by the Society in acquiring life skills and attending community development programs.
Today, the JHSLM has expanded its services to assist people with complex needs achieve greater independence and value their positive contributions to society. While the JHSLM continues to advocate for and support people impacted by the criminal justice system, the organization has developed an expertise in assisting people facing multiple barriers, including those who may be experiencing homelessness, unemployment, problematic substance abuse, mental health challenges, developmental disabilities, or spectrum disorders. This is done through a range of programs that provide assistance with housing, life-skills, education, employment, and community-based services, with the goal of creating a safe, healthy and inclusive community for all.
The Society is also involved in parole, probation, bail supervision and community assessments, lessening the demands on existing facilities. In the area of education, the Society provides speakers for service clubs, churches and community groups desiring information about the criminal justice system and for furthering the cause of penal reform. In the area of advocacy, the Society's staff has been involved in preparing briefs and papers and corresponding with Government officials and others in an attempt to monitor the criminal justice system and encourage alternatives.
Organizationally, the John Howard Society of BC and the Vancouver Office of the JHS operated under the same roof and had the same executive director until 1983 when the provincial office was removed to Victoria, physically separated from any local branch office. At that time the JHS of BC and the JHS of Vancouver Island were amalgamated. The Vancouver office became the John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland of BC. There are currently seven regional John Howard Society’s in BC, and one provincial organization which now operates in the same office as the JHSLM.
published
Full
Revised
Title based on the contents of the fonds.
The records of the John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland of British Columbia consist of the Society's administrative records and client case files and cards used to document information about individual clients. They encompass work done as a provincial society and also as a working office in the Lower Mainland.
The administrative records of the Society document all aspects of the Society's work. They are broken down into three separate series, reflecting the particular manner in which the Society operated. First, a separate series of miscellaneous records which the Society appears to have kept apart from its established file system dates from 1932 to 1988. A second series of administrative records dating from 1932 to about 1968 reflects the Society's file classification plan in use at the time (see Appendix B1 - hard-copy finding aid only). A third group of administrative records reflects a new file classification plan which replaced the earlier file system (see Appendix B2 - hard-copy finding aid only). Administrative records that have accrued to the fonds have been added to this series.
Later records demonstrate the increased activity of the society in addressing the social problems of crime, including victim assistance programs and community assessments, as well as administration of halfway houses.
Individual case files and cards provide evidence of the Society's involvement with clients on probation including repeat or 'habitual' offenders, as well as prison visits, counseling sessions and other related actions undertaken by the Society on behalf of its clients.
Records comprising this fonds are records created at the Vancouver office of the Society, and do not include records created by the various regional offices.
Arrangement of this fonds has been challenging because the organization operated as both a provincial society and a working branch office for most of its years. As such, the records for these 2 functions are intermingled. The accrual of later records firmly cements the arrangement as the JHS of the Lower Mainland of BC. Consequently, the name of the fonds has changed from the John Howard Society of British Columbia to the John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland of British Columbia. Most of the administrative records have been added to the existing 3rd series F-1-3 and new series have been added for Habituals, Victim assistance program, Completed community assessments, Parolee card file, Closing reports, and Executive director records.
Photographic materials; Textual records; Records in electronic form (born-digital); Health and social services; Law and justice
The records of the John Howard Society of British Columbia were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives in January 1993 by the John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland. A donation agreement was entered into between the John Howard Society and the Archives involving the transfer of ownership and matters pertaining to access and confidentiality of information contained in the files.
An Agreement to Transfer was signed in 1998 that bound the JHS of the Lower Mainalnd of BC to transfer its records every five yars beginning in 1999. Accordingly, an accrual to the existing donation was made in 1999.
It is expected that future accruals of the John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland, the local body now carrying out program areas of the Society, will be acquired by Simon Fraser University Archives.
The records of the John Howard Society of Vancouver Island, a separate and independent John Howard Society, are held at the University of British Columbia Library, University Archives Division.
Pursuant to article 4.03 of the Donation Agreement between the John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland of B.C. and Simon Fraser University, the John Howard Society of British Columbia fonds is subject to the principles of privacy as laid out in the 1992 Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act (c. 61). Part 4.03 of the Agreement on access stipulates that:
"In providing access to any part of the client files, the Archives will act in accordance with the principles of privacy as laid out in the Freedom on Information and Protection of Privacy Act, S.B.C., 1992, c. 61 and such amendments to this Act as may be made from time to time. The University Archivist assumes responsibility for administering access to the records and for interpreting the application of these principles when considering individual requests for research access to these files. The John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland shall be permitted to have access to the Restricted Material, and such access shall be on the conditions set out in the John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland of B.C.'s authorization."
Article 8 of the Agreement refers to the confidentiality of the papers:
"The Archives acknowledges that certain information relating to the activities of the John Howard Society of the Lower Mainland of B.C. is confidential. The Archives shall use its best efforts to maintain the absolute confidentiality of all restricted materials."
Accordingly, files in series F-1-4 (Client case files) and F-1-5 (Client case cards) are restricted in order to protect the personal information and privacy of clients of the John Howard Society. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
Series descriptions and file lists are available. Office file classification plans are available (photocopies) are available in the hard copy version of the finding aid maintained in the Archives Reading Room.
- General administrative and office files, 1924 - 1989; F-1-1; 1.39 m of textual records
  published
  - Minutes, 1931 - 1982; F-1-1-1; 31 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of the official Minutes of the Annual Meetings of the Society from 1932 to 1982, official Minutes of the Board and Executive Committee meetings from 1956 to 1980 and some early reports of the Executive Secretary primarily from the 1930s.
    - Minutes of Annual Meetings - 1st to 19th Annual Meeting, 1932 - 1950; F-1-1-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 1-1)
      Textual records
      Open
    - Minutes of Annual Meetings - 20th to 34th Annual Meeting, 1951 - 1965; F-1-1-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 1-1)
    - Minutes of Annual Meetings - 35th to 51st Annual Meeting, 1966 - 1982; F-1-1-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 1-1)
      Pending review
    - Report of the Executive Secretary, 1931 - 1941; F-1-1-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 1-1)
    - Report of the Executive Secretary, 1937; F-1-1-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 1-1)
    - Minutes of the Meeting of the Executive Committee of the Board of Directors, 1963 - 1972; F-1-1-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 1-1)
    - Minutes of the Meeting of the Board of Directors, 1973 - 1977; F-1-1-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 1-1)
    - Minutes of the Meeting of the Board of Directors, 1978 - 1982; F-1-1-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 1-1)
    - Board and Executive Minutes, 1956 - 1960; F-1-1-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 1-2)
    - Board and Executive Minutes, 1961; F-1-1-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 1-2)
    - Board and Executive Minutes, 1962 - 1965; F-1-1-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 1-2)
      Restricted in part
    - Board and Executive Minutes, 1966 - 1968; F-1-1-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 1-2)
    - Board Minutes, 1969; F-1-1-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 1-2)
    - Board Minutes, 1970; F-1-1-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 1-2)
    - Board and Executive Minutes, 1971 - 1972; F-1-1-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 1-2)
    - Board and Executive Minutes, 1973 - 1974; F-1-1-1-0-16 (Archival box - standard 1-3)
    - Board and Executive Minutes, 1975 - 1978; F-1-1-1-0-17 (Archival box - standard 1-3)
    - Board and Executive Minutes, 1979 - 1980; F-1-1-1-0-18 (Archival box - standard 1-3)
    - Minutes of Quarterly Business Meetings, 1971; F-1-1-1-0-19 (Archival box - standard 1-3)
  - Reports, 1931 - 1988; F-1-1-2; 14 cm of textual records; Physical description:
    Subseries consists of Annual Reports dating from 1932 to 1988, including promotional pamphlets summarizing the Annual Report for some of these years. President's Reports and some Monthly Reports for assorted years are also included in this subseries.
    - Annual Reports, 1932 - 1939; F-1-1-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 1-3)
    - Annual Reports, 1940 - 1949; F-1-1-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 1-3)
    - Annual Reports, 1950 - 1959; F-1-1-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 1-3)
    - Annual Reports, 1960 - 1964; F-1-1-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 1-3)
    - Annual Reports, 1984 - 1988; F-1-1-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 1-3)
    - Annual Reports - pamphlets, 1963 - 1983; F-1-1-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
    - Excerpts from reports, 1931 - 1966; F-1-1-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
    - Annual Meeting Addresses, 1946 - 1969; F-1-1-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
    - Annual Meeting Addresses, 1971 - 1982; F-1-1-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
    - President's Reports, 1958, 1966-1967; F-1-1-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
    - Monthly Reports, 1931 - 1933; F-1-1-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
    - Monthly Reports, 1954; F-1-1-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
  - Board of Directors, 1959 - 1983; F-1-1-3; 5 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of miscellaneous materials pertaining to the Board of Directors and other officials of the Society, including Honourary officers, Ex-Officio members and Elected Directors. Some correspondence is included in these files pertaining to appointments and resignations. A Decision Book of the Executive Committee dating from 1968 to 1984 is also included in the subseries.
    - Board of Directors, 1959 - 1969, 1973; F-1-1-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
    - Board of Directors, 1980 - 1981; F-1-1-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
    - Board of Directors, 1981 - 1982; F-1-1-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
    - Board of Directors, 1982 - 1983; F-1-1-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
    - Decision Book of the Executive Committee, 1963 - 1983; F-1-1-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 1-4)
  - Financial Statements, 1940 - 1981; F-1-1-4; 13 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of files containing official Financial Statements prepared by an accounting firm on behalf of the Society.
    - Finance, Budget and Funds Received, 1980 - 1981; F-1-1-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 1-5)
    - Financial Statements, 1940 - 1961; F-1-1-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 1-5)
    - Financial Statements, 1962 - 1980; F-1-1-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 1-5)
  - John Howard Society (JHS) of Canada, 1957 - 1983; F-1-1-5; 13 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of various files pertaining to the National office of the John Howard Society, including a Memorandum of Agreement dated 1961 between the John Howard of Canada and the John Howard Society of British Columbia and Minutes of the national Executive Directors' meetings for various years from 1971 to 1983.
    John Howard Society of Canada
    - JHS Canada - Constitution, 1971; F-1-1-5-0-1 (Archival box - standard 1-6)
    - JHS Canada - Memorandum of Agreement, 1961; F-1-1-5-0-2 (Archival box - standard 1-6)
    - JHS Canada - Correspondence, 1957 - 1970; F-1-1-5-0-3 (Archival box - standard 1-6)
    - JHS Canada - Ottawa Meeting, 1971; F-1-1-5-0-4 (Archival box - standard 1-6)
    - JHS Canada - Board of Directors Meeting, 1971 - 1973; F-1-1-5-0-5 (Archival box - standard 1-6)
    - JHS Canada - Executive Committee Meeting, 1972; F-1-1-5-0-6 (Archival box - standard 1-6)
    - JHS Canada - Executive Director's Meeting, 1982; F-1-1-5-0-7 (Archival box - standard 1-6)
    - JHS Canada - Executive Director's Meeting, 1983; F-1-1-5-0-8 (Archival box - standard 1-6)
  - Miscellaneous Materials, 1924 - 1989; F-1-1-6; 64 cm of textual records
    Subseries consists of files containing miscellaneous reports, articles and newspaper clippings. Files cover a broad range of subject areas including the John Howard Players, the Victims of Crime Program and early correspondence of Society officials.
    - Jubilee Year, 1981; F-1-1-6-0-1 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - Activity Reports of JHS Committee Programs, 1977 - 1978; F-1-1-6-0-2 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - Brief of the Parliamentary Sub-Committee on the Penitentiary System in Canada, 1976; F-1-1-6-0-3 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - Staff lists, 1981; F-1-1-6-0-4 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - Submission to the Legislative Committee on Welfare, Education and Juvenile Delinquency, 1958; F-1-1-6-0-5 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - Royal Commission on Penal Reform, 1936; F-1-1-6-0-6 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - Family Violence Project at Mission Medium Security Prison, 1980 - 1982; F-1-1-6-0-7 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - John Howard Players, 1963 - 1965; F-1-1-6-0-8 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - Press Releases, 1957 - 1968; F-1-1-6-0-9 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - Newsletters, 1958 - 1973, 1980, 1989; F-1-1-6-0-10 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - Newsletters of other JHS offices, 1959 - 1986; F-1-1-6-0-11 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - Regional Meetings, 1963 - 1967; F-1-1-6-0-12 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - JHS of Vancouver Island, 1975 - 1980; F-1-1-6-0-13 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - JHS of Lower Mainland, 1985 - 1988; F-1-1-6-0-14 (Archival box - standard 1-7)
    - New Haven Borstal Facility, 1938 - 1942; F-1-1-6-0-15 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - The Bridge Club, 1959 - 1960; F-1-1-6-0-16 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - Union, 1963 - 1976; F-1-1-6-0-17 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - Victim Assistance Program, 1981 - 1982; F-1-1-6-0-18 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - Fractured Families, 1972; F-1-1-6-0-19 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - Young Offenders 1930s, 1930 - 1939; F-1-1-6-0-20 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - Female Offenders, 1979; F-1-1-6-0-21 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - Prostitution, 1934 - 1943; F-1-1-6-0-22 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - Prison Reform Recommendations, 1954; F-1-1-6-0-23 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - Submission to Members of Legislative Assembly of B.C., 1969; F-1-1-6-0-24 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - Family Service Fund - Dislocation Transportation, 1979 - 1981; F-1-1-6-0-25 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - Report on Juvenile Delinquency, 1962; F-1-1-6-0-26 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - J.H.S. of Canada - Submission to Ouimet Commission on Crime and Corrections, 1967; F-1-1-6-0-27 (Archival box - standard 1-8)
    - B.C. Youth Council - 1, 1954 - 1958; F-1-1-6-0-28 (Archival box - standard 1-9)
    - B.C. Youth Council - 2, 1956 - 1957; F-1-1-6-0-29 (Archival box - standard 1-9)
    - Brief Submitted to Parliamentary Committee by Juvenile Court Probation Officers, 1957 - 1958; F-1-1-6-0-30 (Archival box - standard 1-9)
    - Constitution and Policy - Branch Relationships, 1957 - 1971; F-1-1-6-0-31 (Archival box - standard 1-9)
    - History, Sources and Documents, F-1-1-6-0-32 (Archival box - standard 1-9)
    - J.B. Hobden - Correspondence, 1937 - 1946; F-1-1-6-0-33 (Archival box - standard 1-9)
    - Office Manual and Procedures, 1959; F-1-1-6-0-34 (Archival box - standard 1-9)
    - Oakalla Prison Farm Statistics, 1924 - 1944; F-1-1-6-0-35 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - JHS Humanitarian Award - Bishop Sovereign, 1932 - 1966; F-1-1-6-0-36 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - Okanagan Operations, 1961 - 1964; F-1-1-6-0-37 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - Okanagan Operations, 1955 - 1958; F-1-1-6-0-38 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1970 - 1979; F-1-1-6-0-39 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - Borstall School and Program, 1951 - 1952; F-1-1-6-0-40 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - Volunteer Program and Citizen Participation Committee, 1974 - 1976; F-1-1-6-0-41 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - Victims of Crime Program, 1980 - 1982; F-1-1-6-0-42 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - Victims Assistance Program, 1982 - 1983; F-1-1-6-0-43 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - Social Work, 1961; F-1-1-6-0-44 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - B. Kyle Stevensen, Assistant Executive Director - Correspondence, 1953 - 1954; F-1-1-6-0-45 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - D.L. Jackson, Assistant to Executive Secretary - Correspondence, 1951 - 1952; F-1-1-6-0-46 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - J.H. Hobden - Correspondence, 1936 - 1950; F-1-1-6-0-47 (Archival box - standard 1-10)
    - Howard House / Hobden House, 1959-1960; 1984; F-1-1-6-0-48 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - C.R.J. Skatfeld - Correspondence, 1963 - 1964; F-1-1-6-0-49; Informal access review by: Richard Dancy. Review date: 2020-01-30. Notes: no restricted information identified. (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - Minutes of Meeting of the Committee on Homeless Men, 1934; F-1-1-6-0-50 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - Provincial Standards, 1978 - 1980; F-1-1-6-0-51 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - Addiction and Treatment - 1930s, 1930 - 1939; F-1-1-6-0-52 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - Prison Visitation, 1957 - 1981; F-1-1-6-0-53 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - Sex Offenders, 1954 - 1983; F-1-1-6-0-54 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - Women and the Law, 1938 - 1979; F-1-1-6-0-55 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - Legal Aid, 1968 - 1989; F-1-1-6-0-56 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - League of Nations, 1934 - 1938; F-1-1-6-0-57 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - Narcotics, 1948 - 1952; F-1-1-6-0-58 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - 25 Years: Anniversary Publication, 1956; F-1-1-6-0-59 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - Board of Directors Meetings 1982/83, 1981 - 1988; F-1-1-6-0-60 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
    - Delinquency Prevention Program, 1979 - 1981; F-1-1-6-0-61 (Archival box - standard 1-11)
- General Administrative and Office Files, 1922 - 1973; F-1-2; 1.66 m of textual records
  Series consists of the main administrative files of the Society from about 1932 to 1973. During this period, a central office filing system was in place where each file category was assigned a unique alpha-numeric code. The alphabetic code was used to represent the broad category or subject area while the numeric code represented a division of the main category.
  Researchers should be aware that the files are not arranged according to strict chronological and alphabetical order within or between subseries, and therefore the entire file list for the subseries below should be reviewed to determine the existence of all files on a particular subject.
  Arranged according to original filing system. The Society's file classification plan in use at the time is reproduced in Appendix B1.
  - Administration, 1931 - 1969; F-1-2-1; 38 cm of textual records